{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Chandragupta Maurya was an ardent follower of __________",
            "optionA": "  Sikhism ",
            "optionB": "  Jainism ",
            "optionC": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionD": "  Jewism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandragupta thereafter built one of the largest empires ever on the Indian subcontinent. According to Jain sources, he then renounced it all, and became a monk in the Jain tradition. Chandragupta is claimed, by the historic Jain texts, to have followed Jainism in his life, by first renouncing all his wealth and power, going away with Jaina monks into the Deccan region (now Karnataka), and ultimately performing Sallekhana - the Jain religious ritual of peacefully welcoming death by fasting. ",
            "keyString": "905299s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arthasastra was written by",
            "optionA": "  Dhanananda ",
            "optionB": "  Kautilya ",
            "optionC": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionD": "  Pushyamitra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arthashastra is the title of a handbook for running an empire, written by Kautilya (also known as Chanakya, c. 350-275 BCE) an Indian statesman and philosopher, chief advisor and Prime Minister of the Indian Emperor Chandragupta, the first ruler of the Mauryan Empire. ",
            "keyString": "905359s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The monk who influenced Ashoka to embrace Buddhism was",
            "optionA": "  Vishnu Gupta ",
            "optionB": "  Upagupta ",
            "optionC": "  Brahma Gupta ",
            "optionD": "  Brihadratha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUpagupta (c. 3rd Century BC) was a Buddhist monk. According to some stories in the Sanskrit text Ashokavadana, he was the spiritual teacher of the Mauryan emperor Ashoka. Upagupta's teacher was Sanavasi who was a disciple of Ananda, the Buddha's attendant. ",
            "keyString": "905554s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Greek Ambassador at the Mauryan Court ?",
            "optionA": "  Alexander ",
            "optionB": "  Megasthanese ",
            "optionC": "  Plato ",
            "optionD": "  Aristotle ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes was born in Asia Minor and became an ambassador of Seleucus I Nicator of the Seleucid dynasty to Chandragupta Maurya in Pataliputra, India. ",
            "keyString": "905713s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The illustrious names of Aryabhatta and Varahamihira are associated with the age of the",
            "optionA": "  Guptas ",
            "optionB": "  Kushanas ",
            "optionC": "  Mauryas ",
            "optionD": "  Palas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gupta Empire was an ancient Indian empire existing from the mid-to-late 3rd century CE to 590 CE. At its zenith, from approximately 319 to 550 CE, it covered much of the Indian subcontinent. This period is called the Golden Age of India by some historians. ",
            "keyString": "905850s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The great silk-route to the Indians was opened by",
            "optionA": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Harsha ",
            "optionD": "  Fa-Hien ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe great silk-route to the Indians was opened by Kaniskha. Silk Route was established during the reign of Han Dynasty of China. It connects China with East Europe Mediterranean countries and Central Asia, passing through India. ",
            "keyString": "978705s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under Mauryas each province was placed under a__________",
            "optionA": "  Prince ",
            "optionB": "  Commander ",
            "optionC": "  Council ",
            "optionD": "  Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe empire was divided into four provinces, each under a prince or member of the royal family (Kumara and Aryaputra). ",
            "keyString": "978901s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Harshavardhana moved his capital from __________ to __________",
            "optionA": "  Thanesar, Kannauj ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi, Deogiri ",
            "optionC": "  Kamboj, Kannauj ",
            "optionD": "  Valabhi, Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThanesar to Kannauj ",
            "keyString": "979073s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Greatest Kushan leader who got converted to Buddhism was",
            "optionA": "  Kujala ",
            "optionB": "  Virna ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Kadphises ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanishka was a great patron of the Buddhist faith; Buddhism spread to Central Asia and the Far East across Bactria and Sogdia, where his empire met the Han Empire of China. King Kanishka was greatly influenced by the knowledge, teachings and personality of the Buddhist scholar Asvaghosha so, he decided to embrace Buddhism in later days of his life. He even accepted the Mahayana sect of Buddhism as his state religion. ",
            "keyString": "979238s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The official language of the Mauryan Court was",
            "optionA": "  Magadhi ",
            "optionB": "  Prakrit ",
            "optionC": "  Mythili ",
            "optionD": "  Sanskrit ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is believed to be the language spoken by Gautama Buddha. It was the official language of the Mauryan court, in which the edicts of Ashoka were composed. The name Magahi is directly derived from the name Magadhi Prakrit, and educated speakers of Magahi prefer to call it \"Magadhi\" rather than \"Magahi\". ",
            "keyString": "982411s59m17h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Yavanika or curtain was introduced in Indian theatre by which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Shakas ",
            "optionB": "  Parthians ",
            "optionC": "  Greeks ",
            "optionD": "  Kushans ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYavanika (Curtain) was introduced in Indian theatre by the Greeks. ",
            "keyString": "111585s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the Satavahana Empire?",
            "optionA": "  Kanha ",
            "optionB": "  Simuka ",
            "optionC": "  Hala ",
            "optionD": "  Gautamiputra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimuka was the founder of the Satavahana Dynasty and he is believed to have destroyed the Shunga Power. He did so with the aid of the Rathikas and Bhojakas. He reigned for around 23 years and was beheaded by his brother Kanha, who succeeded him. ",
            "keyString": "111804s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ghatotkacha (who ruled in the years 290-305 B.C.) was a king from which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Gupta Dynasty ",
            "optionB": "  Kanva Dynasty ",
            "optionC": "  Shunga Dynasty ",
            "optionD": "  Maurya Dynasty ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGhatotkacha (king) was a pre-imperial Gupta king of northern India. He was a son of the dynasty's founder Gupta, and the father of the dynasty's first emperor Chandragupta I. ",
            "keyString": "112109s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following foreigners was the first to visit India?",
            "optionA": "  Hiuen Tsang ",
            "optionB": "  Megasthenese ",
            "optionC": "  I-Tsing ",
            "optionD": "  Fahien ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes is the very first foreigner to be visited India from Greek. He had worked as ambassador of Selecus I of Syria. He came to the court of Sandrokattes who is none other than, the Great Chandragupta Maurya. ",
            "keyString": "112307s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bimbisara was the king of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionB": "  Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Shunga ",
            "optionD": "  Nanda ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBimbisara was the son of Bhattiya, a chieftain. He ascended to throne at the age of 15 in 543 BC. He established the Haryanka dynasty laid the foundations of Magadha by fortification of a village, which later became the city of Pataliputra. Bimbisara's first capital was at Girivraja (identified with Rajagriha). ",
            "keyString": "112490s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who usurped power from the Mauryas after killing the last Mauryan ruler Brihadratha?",
            "optionA": "  Pushyamitra Sunga ",
            "optionB": "  Agnimitra ",
            "optionC": "  Vasumitra ",
            "optionD": "  Jyesthamitra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrihadratha Maurya was killed in 180 BCE and power usurped by his general, Pushyamitra Shunga, who then took over the throne and established the Shunga Empire. ",
            "keyString": "211699s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chandra Gupta Maurya spent his last days here",
            "optionA": "  Kashi ",
            "optionB": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionC": "  Ujjain ",
            "optionD": "  Shravanabelagola ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring his last days Chandragupta accepted Jainsim and spent his last days at Sravanabelagola with Bhadrabahu. ",
            "keyString": "211741s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bindusara was the son of?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Shivaji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBindusara was the second Mauryan emperor of India. He was the son of the dynasty's founder Chandragupta, and the father of its most famous ruler Ashoka. ",
            "keyString": "211759s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The rulers of which dynasty started the practice of granting tax-free villages to Brahmanas and Buddhist Monks?",
            "optionA": "  Satavahanas ",
            "optionB": "  Mauryas ",
            "optionC": "  Guptas ",
            "optionD": "  Cholas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Satavahanas started the practice of granting tax-free villages to brahmanas and Buddhist monks. The cultivated fields and villages granted to them were declared free from intrusion by royal policemen, soldiers, and other royal officers. These areas therefore became small independent islands within the Satavahana kingdom. ",
            "keyString": "211775s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was not a characteristic of society in Mauryan times?",
            "optionA": "  Slavery ",
            "optionB": "  Rigidity of Caste ",
            "optionC": "  Prostitution ",
            "optionD": "  Widow remarriage ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlthough societies frowned on remarriage, widow remarriage was not unusual when the women's surviving family was not able to support her and her children or did not have a male of sufficient age to ensure the family's future. ",
            "keyString": "211790s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Greek ambassador sent to Chandragupta\nMaurya's Court was",
            "optionA": "  Kautilya ",
            "optionB": "  Seleucus Nicator ",
            "optionC": "  Megasthenes ",
            "optionD": "  Justin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeleucus dispatched an ambassador, Megasthenes, to Chandragupta, and later Antiochos sent Deimakos to his son Bindusara, at the Maurya court at Pataliputra (modern Patna in Bihar state). ",
            "keyString": "287965s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chandragupta Maurya was born in",
            "optionA": "  340 BC ",
            "optionB": "  563 BC ",
            "optionC": "  189 BC ",
            "optionD": "  99 BC ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChandragupta Maurya was born in 340 BC in Pataliputra, in modern-day Bihar. His background is, however, uncertain. Some claim that he was born to a Nanda prince and his maid-servant, Mura, from the Shudra caste, while others state that he belonged to the Moriya tribe of Peacock-tamers. ",
            "keyString": "288106s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bindusara sent Ashoka to quell the rebellion in",
            "optionA": "  Swarnagiri ",
            "optionB": "  Taxila ",
            "optionC": "  Ujjain ",
            "optionD": "  Tosali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mahavamsa suggests that Bindusara appointed his son Ashoka as the viceroy of Ujjayini. Ashokavadana states that Bindusara sent Ashoka to lay siege to Takshashila. The Emperor refused to provide any weapons or chariots for Ashoka's expedition. ",
            "keyString": "288153s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the principal source of information of Ashoka's campaign against Kalinga?",
            "optionA": "  Pillar Edict-VII ",
            "optionB": "  Mahavamsa ",
            "optionC": "  Divyavadana ",
            "optionD": "  Rock Edict-XIII ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rock edict XIII gives a clue that Kalinga was a country previously unconquered, thus Ashoka's declaration of war was that of unprovoked aggression. The Kalinga war witnessed terrible manslaughter and destruction. Asoka's victory in the Kalinga war followed by remorse. Victory of morality in India and among the Greeks (Yonas), as far as where the Greek kings Antiochus, Ptolemy, Antigonus, Magas and Alexander rule. ",
            "keyString": "288188s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Greeks were driven out of India by",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Vikramaditya ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Bindusara ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnd it is after Alexander's death in 323 BC., that Chandragupta is said to have put an end to the Greek rule in northwest India, returned to Magadha, killed the Nanda king, and proclaimed the Maurya dynasty in 322 BC. ",
            "keyString": "288222s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following dynasty succeeded the Mauryas?",
            "optionA": "  Satavahanas ",
            "optionB": "  Sungas ",
            "optionC": "  Yavanas ",
            "optionD": "  Pandya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe dynasty was established by Pushyamitra Shunga, after the fall of the Maurya Empire. Its capital was Pataliputra, but later emperors such as Bhagabhadra also held court at Besnagar (modern Vidisha) in eastern Malwa. Pushyamitra Shunga ruled for 36 years and was succeeded by his son Agnimitra. ",
            "keyString": "371312s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the court physician of Kanishka?",
            "optionA": "  Vasumitra ",
            "optionB": "  Nagarjuna ",
            "optionC": "  Charaka ",
            "optionD": "  Patanjali ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharaka was the court physician of Kanishka I. He was one of the principal contributors to the ancient art and science of Ayurveda, a system of medicine and lifestyle developed in Ancient India. He is sometimes referred to as the Father of Indian Medicine. ",
            "keyString": "371425s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the Saka Era which is still used by the Government of India?",
            "optionA": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionB": "  Vikramaditya ",
            "optionC": "  Samudra Gupta ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe beginning of the Shaka era is now widely equated to the ascension of king Chashtana in 78 CE. His inscriptions, dated to the years 11 and 52, have been found at Andhau in Kutch region. These years are interpreted as Shaka years 11 (89 CE) and 52 (130 CE). A previously more common view was that the beginning of the Shaka era corresponds to the ascension of Kanishka I in 78 CE.",
            "keyString": "371471s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. The Arthashastra, attributed to the Mauryan minister Chanakya in the 4th Century B.C., is one of the earliest Indian texts devoted to political philosophy, and it discusses ideas of statecraft and economic policy.\nII. During the Indian struggle for independence in the early 20th Century, Mahatma Gandhi popularized the philosophies of ahimsa (non-violence) and satyagraha (non-violent resistance),\nIII. Gandhian Philosophy was influenced by the teachings of the Hindu Bhagavad Gita, as well as Jesus, Tolstoy, Thoreau and Ruskin.\nWhich of the above statement(s) is/are correct related to the Indian Political Philosophy?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  I, II & III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arthashastra, attributed to the Mauryan minister Chanakya in the 4th Century B.C., is one of the earliest Indian texts devoted to political philosophy, and it discusses ideas of statecraft and economic policy. During the Indian struggle for independence in the early 20th Century, Mahatma Gandhi popularized the philosophies of ahimsa (non-violence) and satyagraha (non-violent resistance), which were influenced by the teachings of the Hindu Bhagavad Gita, as well as Jesus, Tolstoy, Thoreau and Ruskin. ",
            "keyString": "371507s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological sequence of the ruling dynasties of northern India, from the decline of the Mauryas to the rise of the imperial Guptas?",
            "optionA": "  Sungas, Indo-Greeks, Kushans, Sakas and Guptas ",
            "optionB": "  Sungas, Kushans, Parthians, Sakas and Guptas ",
            "optionC": "  Sungas, Kanvas, Indo-Greeks, Sakas, Parthians and Guptas ",
            "optionD": "  Kanvas, Sungas, Indo-Greeks, Sakas, Parthians and Guptas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSungas, Kanvas, Indo-Greeks, Sakas, Parthians and Guptas is the correct chronological sequence of the ruling dynasties of northern India, from the decline of the Mauryas to the rise of the imperial Guptas. ",
            "keyString": "371547s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mauryan period the administration was in the hands of",
            "optionA": "  three boards ",
            "optionB": "  four boards ",
            "optionC": "  five boards ",
            "optionD": "  six boards ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe officials were divided into six committees each with a membership of five. The first committee was concerned with matters relating to industrial arts. The second occupied it with the facilities to the foreigners. The third kept a register of births and deaths both by way of a census and for purposes of taxation. The fourth committee was in charge of matters of trade and commerce. The fifth committee supervised the public sale of manufactured articles. The sixth commit\u00adtee collected the tax on the articles sold, this being one-tenth of the purchase price. ",
            "keyString": "426099s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Chandragupta Maurya failed in his first campaign against Magadha.\nReason (R): He did not begin with the frontiers, but invaded the heart of Magadha.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maurya Empire was a geographically-extensive Iron Age historical power based in Magadha and founded by Chandragupta Maurya which dominated ancient India between 322 and 187 BCE.",
            "keyString": "497714s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sultan of Delhi who transferred two monolithic Mauryan pillars to Delhi to beautify his capital, was",
            "optionA": "  Iltutmish ",
            "optionB": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionC": "  Firuz Tughluq ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammad-bin-Tughluq ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFiruz Tughluq, The Sultan of Delhi who transferred two monolithic Mauryan pillars to Delhi to beautify his capital. Sultan Firuz Shah Tughlaq was a Turkic Muslim ruler of the Tughlaq Dynasty, who reigned over the Sultanate of Delhi from 1351 to 1388. His father's name was Rajab who had the title Sipahsalar. ",
            "keyString": "497748s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Monk whom Chandragupta Maurya accompanied to South India was __________",
            "optionA": "  Asvaghosa ",
            "optionB": "  Vasumitra ",
            "optionC": "  Upagupta ",
            "optionD": "  Bhadrabahu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAcharya Bhadrabahu (c. 367 - c. 298 BCE) was, according to the Digambara sect of Jainism, the last Shruta Kevalin in Jainism. He was the last acharya of the undivided Jain sangha. He was the last spiritual teacher of Chandragupta Maurya. ",
            "keyString": "497762s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who were the first kings to issue gold coins in India?",
            "optionA": "  Mauryas ",
            "optionB": "  Indo-Greeks ",
            "optionC": "  Guptas ",
            "optionD": "  Kushans ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indo-Greeks were the first rulers in India to issue coins which can definitely be attributed to the kings. They were the first to issue gold coins in India. ",
            "keyString": "497774s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mauryan sculptors had attained the highest perfection in the carving of",
            "optionA": "  floral designs ",
            "optionB": "  pillars ",
            "optionC": "  animal figures ",
            "optionD": "  yaksha figures ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mauryan sculptors had attained the highest perfection in the carving of animal figure. Stone pillars were erected all over the Mauryan Empire. The top portion of the pillar was carved with figures like a bull, lion, elephant, etc. All the capital figures (usually animals) are vigorous and carved standing on a square or circular abacus. ",
            "keyString": "497785s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Greek ambassador in the court of Chandragupta Maurya?",
            "optionA": "  Megasthanes ",
            "optionB": "  Seleucos ",
            "optionC": "  Menander ",
            "optionD": "  Demetrias ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes was born in Asia Minor and became an ambassador of Seleucus I Nicator of the Seleucid dynasty to Chandragupta Maurya in Pataliputra, India. ",
            "keyString": "600446s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not one of the actual cause for the decline of the Mauryan empire?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka's pacifist policies ",
            "optionB": "  Division of the empire after Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Foreign aggressions particularly Greek ",
            "optionD": "  Economic and financial crisis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe decline of the Maurya Dynasty was rather rapid after the death of Ashoka/Asoka. One obvious reason for it was the succession of weak kings. Another immediate cause was the partition of the Empire into two. Had not the partition taken place, the Greek invasions could have been held back giving a chance to the Mauryas to re-establish some degree of their previous power. Mauryan Empire began to decline after the death of Ashoka in 232 BC. The last king was Brihadratha was assassinated by his general Pushyamitra Shunga who was a Brahmin. ",
            "keyString": "600599s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Satvahanas minted their coins predominantly in",
            "optionA": "  Lead ",
            "optionB": "  Silver ",
            "optionC": "  Gold ",
            "optionD": "  Copper ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Satvahanas predominantly minted their coins in lead. They also used 'potin' an alloy of silver and copper to mint coins. ",
            "keyString": "600653s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most commonly used coin during the Mauryan period was",
            "optionA": "  Karashopana ",
            "optionB": "  Nishka ",
            "optionC": "  Suvarna ",
            "optionD": "  Kakini ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most commonly used coin during the Mauryan period was karashopana. ",
            "keyString": "600729s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dharmamahamatras were __________ during the Mauryans",
            "optionA": "  Officials ",
            "optionB": "  Buddhist Monks ",
            "optionC": "  Jain Monks ",
            "optionD": "  Soldiers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Mahamatra (meaning \"Officer of high rank\") was an \"officer of morality\" established by the Indian Emperor Ashoka (reigned 269-233 BCE). Their full title was Dha\u1e43ma Mahamata, the \"Inspectors of the Dharma\". They were apparently a class of senior officials who were in charge various aspects of administration and justice. ",
            "keyString": "601015s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who took the throne after Chandragupta Maurya?",
            "optionA": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionD": "  Vishnugupta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 298 BCE, Chandragupta voluntarily abdicated the throne in favour of his son Bindusara, who became the new Mauryan emperor. What we know after this point seems closer to legend than an actual historical account. It is said that Chandragupta turned into an ascetic and follower of Jainism. ",
            "keyString": "662608s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Mauryan dynasty Kalinga war took place in the year",
            "optionA": "  260 BC ",
            "optionB": "  261 BC ",
            "optionC": "  126 BC ",
            "optionD": "  232 BC ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka lead a huge army against Kalinga. This took place in 261 BC, the freedom loving people of Kalinga offered a stiff resistance to the Mauryan army. ",
            "keyString": "662644s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following item was collected only in cash under the Mauryas?",
            "optionA": "  Kara ",
            "optionB": "  Bhaga ",
            "optionC": "  Pranaya ",
            "optionD": "  Hiranya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPranaya literally meaning a gift of affection, pranaya was a levy imposed by the state during emergency periods. Though first mentioned by Panini, it was elaborated upon for the first time in Arthashastra. Pranaya amounted to one\u00adthird or one-fourth of the produce according to the nature of the soil. ",
            "keyString": "662658s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mauryan king holds the title of Amitraghata?",
            "optionA": "  Bimbisar ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBindusara is also known as Amitraghata (amitra-enemy, ghata-slayer) in Sanskrit Literature. Strabo has named him Amitrochates or Allitrochades which are greek version of the name Amitraghata. ",
            "keyString": "662670s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chandragupta Maurya with the help of Chanakya decided to overthrow the Nandas because",
            "optionA": "  Chanakya had been humiliated by the Nandas ",
            "optionB": "  the Nandas were low-born ",
            "optionC": "  the Nandas had accumulated a great deal of wealth by extortion and oppression of the people ",
            "optionD": "  Chanakya wanted to restore the ideal of Kshatriya rule ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Chandragupta Maurya with the help of Chanakya decided to overthrow the Nandas because the Nandas accumulated a great deal of wealth by extortion and oppression of the people. ",
            "keyString": "662681s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The last Mauryan king was",
            "optionA": "  Pushyamitra Sunga ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Harsha ",
            "optionD": "  Brihadratha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrihadratha Maurya was the last ruler of the Maurya Empire. He ruled from c. 187 \u2013 c. 180 BCE. He was killed by his general, Pushyamitra Shunga, who went on to establish the Shunga Empire. ",
            "keyString": "739947s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How did the Maurya Empire finally end?",
            "optionA": "  The last Mauryan ruler was killed by his General ",
            "optionB": "  The Kanvas of Central India deposed the last Mauryan ruler ",
            "optionC": "  The last Mauryan ruler was killed in a battle with the foreign invader from the north-west ",
            "optionD": "  The last mauryan ruler had no heir and the throne was claimed by one of his powerful ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the death of Ashoka, the Mauryan empire did not get strong rulers and the empire became weak and later the last ruler of the dynasty, Brihadratha Maurya got killed by his own senapati Pushyamitra Shunga and then Mauryan empire came to an end and the Shunga dynasty came in power. ",
            "keyString": "740123s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The one most important feature of the Mauryan Administration was",
            "optionA": "  wide powers enjoyed by the provincial governors ",
            "optionB": "  the presence of a 'council of ministers' ",
            "optionC": "  the presence of vast, numerous powers of the bureaucracy ",
            "optionD": "  an extensive network of spy-system ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe one most important feature of the Mauryan Administration was the presence of vast, numerous powers of the bureaucracy. ",
            "keyString": "740178s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who amongst the following also had the name 'Devanama Piyadassi'?",
            "optionA": "  Mauryan King Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Mauryan King Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Gautam Buddha ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagwan Mahavira ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka the Great known also as Piyadasi (Pali. Sanskrit:Priyadarsin \u2013 meaning 'good looking'), and Devana\u014bpiya was the emperor of the Mauryan Empire from 273 BCE to 232 BCE. Ten years (of reign) having been completed, King Piodasses (Piyadassi) made known (the doctrine of) Piety to men; and from this moment he has made men more pious, and everything thrives throughout the whole world.",
            "keyString": "740209s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the reign of Bindusara there was unrest at __________",
            "optionA": "  Ujjayani ",
            "optionB": "  Pushkalavati ",
            "optionC": "  Taxila ",
            "optionD": "  Rajagriha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the reign of Bindusara the people of Taxila rose against the Magadha empire to quell that agitation Bindusara sent Ashoka at Taxila. Upon the civil unrest in the kingdom, Nanda resigned and disappeared into exile. ",
            "keyString": "740247s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Rock Edict Ashoka mentions about the casualities of Kalinga War and declares the renunciation of war?",
            "optionA": "  Maski Edict ",
            "optionB": "  Rock Edict XIII ",
            "optionC": "  Rock Edict XI ",
            "optionD": "  Rock Edict X ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rock edict XIII gives a clue that Kalinga was a country previously unconquered, thus Ashoka's declaration of war was that of unprovoked aggression. The Kalinga war witnessed terrible manslaughter and destruction. ",
            "keyString": "808079s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Seleucus Nicator was defeated by",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Bindu Sara ",
            "optionD": "  Brihadratha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Seleucid\u2013Mauryan War was fought between 305 and 303 BCE. It started when Seleucus I Nicator, of the Seleucid Empire, sought to retake the Indian satrapies of the Macedonian Empire which had been occupied by Emperor Chandragupta Maurya, of the Maurya Empire. ",
            "keyString": "808218s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is the oldest dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Gupta ",
            "optionC": "  Kushan ",
            "optionD": "  Kanva ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMauryan Dynasty was the first dynasty in 3rd - 4th Centuries BCE, that unified the subcontinent and contributed in spreading religion (Buddhism). ",
            "keyString": "808259s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ashoka spread Buddhism all over India and Ceylon by",
            "optionA": "  Teaching the Triratnas ",
            "optionB": "  Sending the Dharma Mahamantras ",
            "optionC": "  Wagins wars ",
            "optionD": "  Becoming a Buddhist Monk ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAshoka became a upasaka of Buddha. He establishedan intimate relation with the Buddhist Sangha and is said to have become a monk. He undertook Dharma yatra instructing Dharma to the people. He took up pilgrimages to thebirth place of the Sakyamuni. To spread the message of Dharma to the vast extent of his empire. He appointed officers in charge of religious propagation. They were called Dharma Mahamatras, to spread his ideas of Dharma and spread Buddhism all over India and Ceylon. ",
            "keyString": "808294s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mauryan Dynasty was founded by",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Pushyamitra ",
            "optionD": "  Ajatasatru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maurya Empire was founded in 322 BCE by Chandragupta Maurya, who had overthrown the Nanda Dynasty and rapidly expanded his power westward across central and western India in order to take advantage of the disruptions of local powers in the wake of the withdrawal by Alexander the Great 's armies. ",
            "keyString": "808331s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The capital of the Mauryan kingdom was located at",
            "optionA": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionB": "  Vaishali ",
            "optionC": "  Lumbini ",
            "optionD": "  Gaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maurya Empire was centralized by conquering the Indo-Gangetic Plain in the eastern extent of the empire and had its capital city at Pataliputra (modern Patna). ",
            "keyString": "928658s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following could be the most accurate\ndescription of the Mauryan monarchy under Ashoka?",
            "optionA": "  Enlightened despotism ",
            "optionB": "  Centralised autocracy ",
            "optionC": "  Oriental despotism ",
            "optionD": "  Guided democracy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most accurate description of The Mauryan monarchy under Ashoka was Enlightened despotism. ",
            "keyString": "928781s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mohammed-bin-Qasim conquered Sindh in the year",
            "optionA": "  712 AD ",
            "optionB": "  812 AD ",
            "optionC": "  912 AD ",
            "optionD": "  1012 AD ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Arab invasion of Sindh (712 AD), Muhammad bin Qasim first attacked Debal, a word derived from Deval meaning temple. It was situated on the sea-coast not far from modern Karachi. It was garrisoned by 4000 Kshatriya soldiers and served by 3000 Brahmans. All males of the age of seventeen and upwards were put to the sword and their women and children were enslaved. \"700 beautiful females, who were under the protection of Budh (that is, had taken shelter in the temple), were all captured with their valuable ornaments, and clothes adorned with jewels.\" Muhammad despatched one-fifth of the legal spoil to Hajjaj which included seventy-five damsels, the rest four-fifths were distributed among the soldiers. ",
            "keyString": "928807s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best specimens of Mauryan art are represented by their",
            "optionA": "  Stupas ",
            "optionB": "  Pillars ",
            "optionC": "  Chaityas ",
            "optionD": "  Caves ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt represented an important transition in Indian art from use of wood to stone. It was a royal art patronized by Mauryan kings especially Ashoka. Pillars are the most prominent examples. ",
            "keyString": "928824s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chandragupta Maurya was__________",
            "optionA": "  A benevolent despot ",
            "optionB": "  Autocrat ",
            "optionC": "  Democrat ",
            "optionD": "  A pious ruler ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maurya king was an absolute ruler. He was at the apex of administration. His ideal of kingship was benevolent despotism. The main principle of administration was welfare of the people. ",
            "keyString": "928840s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which dynasty ruled over 'Magadha' after Mauryan Dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Satavahan ",
            "optionB": "  Shunga ",
            "optionC": "  Nanda ",
            "optionD": "  Kanva ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Shunga dynasty was a Brahmin dynasty, established in 185 BCE, about 50 years after Ashoka's death, when the emperor Brihadratha Maurya, the last ruler of the Maurya Empire, was assassinated by his Senani or commander-in-chief, Pushyamitra Shunga, while he was reviewing the Guard of Honour of his forces. ",
            "keyString": "990860s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which of the following centres of learning, Chanakya the famous teacher of Chandragupta Maurya, was associated?",
            "optionA": "  Taxila ",
            "optionB": "  Nalanda ",
            "optionC": "  Vikramshila ",
            "optionD": "  Vaishali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTaxila had great influence on Hindu culture and the Sanskrit language. It is perhaps best known for its association with Chanakya, also known as Kautilya, the strategist who guided Chandragupta Maurya and assisted in the founding of the Mauryan empire. ",
            "keyString": "990906s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The decline of the Nandas at the hands of Kautilya and Chandragupta Maurya has been vividly portrayed in the Sanskrit play written by Kalidasa",
            "optionA": "  Mudrarakshas ",
            "optionB": "  Devichandragupta ",
            "optionC": "  Malavikagnimitram ",
            "optionD": "  Mrichhakatika ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Malavikagnimitram is a Sanskrit play by Kalidasa. It is his first play. The play tells the story of the love of Agnimitra, the Shunga Emperor at Vidisha, for the beautiful lun-maiden of his chief queen. He falls in love with the picture of an exiled servant girl named Malavika. ",
            "keyString": "991046s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is called as the 'second Ashoka' ?",
            "optionA": "  Samudra Gupta ",
            "optionB": "  Chandra Gupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Kanishka ",
            "optionD": "  Harshavardhana ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKushana king Kanishka is also called \"Second Ashoka\". Like Ashoka, Kanishka also became a convert to Buddhism. Kanishka I or Kanishka the Great, was the emperor of the Kushan dynasty in the second century (c. 127\u2013150 CE). He is famous for his military, political, and spiritual achievements. ",
            "keyString": "991154s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the author of the Kadambari, a great romantic play?",
            "optionA": "  Banabhatta ",
            "optionB": "  Harshavardhana ",
            "optionC": "  Baskarvardhana ",
            "optionD": "  Bindusara ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKadambari is a romantic novel in Sanskrit. It was substantially composed by Ba\u1e47abhatta in the first half of the 7th century CE, who did not survive to see it through completion. The novel was completed by Banabhatta's son Bhushanabhatta, according to the plan laid out by his late father. It is conventionally divided into Purvabhaga (earlier part) written by Banabhatta, and Uttarabhaga (latter part) by Bhushanabhatta. (An alternate tradition gives the son's name as Pulindabhatta.)",
            "keyString": "991252s0m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The year of accession of Kanishka to throne was",
            "optionA": "  108 AD ",
            "optionB": "  78 AD ",
            "optionC": "  58 AD ",
            "optionD": "  128AD ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEarlier scholars believed that Kanishka ascended the Kushan throne in 78 CE, and that this date was used as the beginning of the Saka calendar era. However, historians no longer regard this date as that of Kanishka's accession. ",
            "keyString": "33577s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not represent an important source material for the Mauryan period?",
            "optionA": "  Literary works ",
            "optionB": "  Foreign accounts ",
            "optionC": "  Numismatic evidence ",
            "optionD": "  Epigraphic sources ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNumismatic evidence indicates that they controlled territory in the subcontinent until the beginning of the Common Era. The Scythian tribes, renamed Indo-Scythians, brought about the demise of the Indo-Greeks in 70 B.C.E., seizing the region of Mathura, and Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "33621s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The capital of Kanishka was",
            "optionA": "  Puruspura ",
            "optionB": "  Benares ",
            "optionC": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionD": "  Sarnath ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPurushapura(Peshawar) was the capital of Kanishka. ",
            "keyString": "33738s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Charak was the famous court physician of",
            "optionA": "  Harsha ",
            "optionB": "  Chandra Gupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCharak was the court physician of Kanishka I. He was one of the principal contributors to the ancient art and science of Ayurveda, a system of medicine and lifestyle developed in Ancient India. He is sometimes referred to as the Father of Indian Medicine. ",
            "keyString": "33841s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following has written the play of Mudrarakshasa (narrates the ascent of the king Chandragupta Maurya)?",
            "optionA": "  Kautilya ",
            "optionB": "  Vishakhadatta ",
            "optionC": "  Kalidasa ",
            "optionD": "  Panini ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mudrarakshasa is a Sanskrit-language play by Vishakhadatta that narrates the ascent of the king Chandragupta Maurya ( r . c. 324 \u2013 c. 297 BCE) to power in India.",
            "keyString": "33940s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest development in the Kushana period was in the field of",
            "optionA": "  Religion ",
            "optionB": "  Art ",
            "optionC": "  Literature ",
            "optionD": "  Architecture ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe art and culture of Gandhara, at the crossroads of the Kushan hegemony, continued the traditions of Greco-Buddhist art and are the best known expressions of Kushan influences to Westerners.",
            "keyString": "98752s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the spatial (Sthaanik) during Mauryan's period?",
            "optionA": "  District Administrator ",
            "optionB": "  Provincial Administrator ",
            "optionC": "  Village Administrator ",
            "optionD": "  City Administrator ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSthaanik were the District Administrator in Maurayan Empire. Provinces were subdivided into districts for purposes of administration, and a group of officials worked in each district.",
            "keyString": "98799s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following mentioned division of the Mauryan Society into seven classes?",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka's Edicts ",
            "optionB": "  Indica ",
            "optionC": "  Kautilya's Arthshastra ",
            "optionD": "  Vishnu Purana ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndica is the book written by Megasthenes, the Greek ambassador to India around 300 Be. The division of Maurya society into seven classes was particularly mentioned in the 'Indica' of Megasthenes. The Indians generally were divided into seven categories, the wise men (Brahmins), farmers, herdsmen, artisans, soldiers, over lookers and government officials including army and navy officers. ",
            "keyString": "98935s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who, among the following, was not a part of the Mauryan dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Ajatsatru ",
            "optionB": "  Bindusara ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjatshatru was born in 492 BC that is approx 200 years before Maurya. Ajatshatru was the king of Haryanka dynasty of Magadh having his capital as Rajgir. ",
            "keyString": "99064s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kalinga's ruler Kharavela gave his protection to",
            "optionA": "  Hinduism ",
            "optionB": "  Shaivism ",
            "optionC": "  Buddhism ",
            "optionD": "  Jainism ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKharavela was a king of Kalinga in present-day Odisha, India. He ruled somewhere around first or second century BCE. Kharavela is believed to be a follower of Jainism, although the Hathigumpha inscription describes him as a worshipper of all religious orders. ",
            "keyString": "103162s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Upto where did Chandragupta Maurya's empire extend in the north west?",
            "optionA": "  Ravi river ",
            "optionB": "  Indus river ",
            "optionC": "  Satluj river ",
            "optionD": "  Hindukush range ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the Buddhist text Mahavamsa tika, Chandragupta and his guru Chanakya began recruiting an army after he completed his studies at Taxila (now in Pakistan). This was a period of wars, given that Alexander the Great had invaded the northwest subcontinent from Caucasus Indicus (also called Paropamisadae in ancient texts, now called the Hindu Kush mountain range). ",
            "keyString": "156260s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Alexander and Porus fought a battle at",
            "optionA": "  Hydaspes ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Panipat ",
            "optionD": "  Train ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of the Hydaspes was fought in 326 BC between Alexander the Great and King Porus of the Paurava kingdom on the banks of the river Jhelum (known to the Greeks as Hydaspes) in the Punjab region of the Indian subcontinent (modern-day Punjab, Pakistan). ",
            "keyString": "156301s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following were contemporaries of Kanishka?",
            "optionA": "  Kamban, Banabhatta, Ashvagosha ",
            "optionB": "  Nagarjuna, Ashvagosha, Vasumitra ",
            "optionC": "  Asvagosha, Kalidasa, Banabhatta ",
            "optionD": "  Kalidas, Kamba, Vasumitra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarjuna- the Mahayana Philosopher. Ashvagosha- the poet, Musician and Buddhist Monk. Vasumitra-the Buddhist Monk who presided the fourth Buddhist council. All of these were contemporary to Kushana Ruler Kanishka. ",
            "keyString": "156409s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With whom is 'Junagarh Rock Inscription' associated?",
            "optionA": "  Rudradaman ",
            "optionB": "  Bimbisara ",
            "optionC": "  Chandragupta-II ",
            "optionD": "  Gautamiputra Satakarni ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Junagadh rock inscription of Rudradaman, also known as the Girnar Rock inscription of Rudradaman, is a Sanskrit prose inscribed on a rock by the Western Satraps ruler Rudradaman I. It is located near Girnar hill near Junagadh, Gujarat, India. The inscription is dated to shortly after 150 CE. ",
            "keyString": "156511s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who amidst the following was a wife of emperor Ashoka who influenced him?",
            "optionA": "  Chandalika ",
            "optionB": "  Charulata ",
            "optionC": "  Gautami ",
            "optionD": "  Karuwaki ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Karuvaki was the second queen of the third Mauryan emperor, Ashoka. She was also the mother of Ashoka's son, Prince Tivala. ",
            "keyString": "156605s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who were the immediate successors of the Mauryas in Magadha?",
            "optionA": "  Pandyas ",
            "optionB": "  Sungas ",
            "optionC": "  Kushanas ",
            "optionD": "  Satvahanas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Shunga Empire was an ancient Indian dynasty from Magadha that controlled areas of the central and eastern Indian subcontinent from around 187 to 78 BCE. The dynasty was established by Pushyamitra Shunga, after the fall of the Maurya Empire. ",
            "keyString": "206255s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Megasthanes, the ambassador of Selucus at the Mauryan court in Pataliputra, wrote an account of the period in his book",
            "optionA": "  Travels of Megasthanes ",
            "optionB": "  Indika ",
            "optionC": "  Indicoplecusts ",
            "optionD": "  Both (B) and (C) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes was an ancient Greek historian, diplomat and Indian ethnographer and explorer in the Hellenistic period. He described India in his book Indika, which is now lost, but has been partially reconstructed from the writings of the later authors. ",
            "keyString": "206435s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following do we come across a detailed account of the municipal administration of Mauryas?",
            "optionA": "  The Arthashastra of Kautilya ",
            "optionB": "  The account of Megasthenes ",
            "optionC": "  The Mudrarakshasa ",
            "optionD": "  Mauryan inscription ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMegasthenes describes the administration of the armed forces as comprising of six committees with five members on each. The first committee was concerned with naval warfare, second equivalent to the modern commissariat supervising the transport of war materials, third supervising the infantry, the fourth supervising cavalry, the fifth was concerned with chariots and the sixth supervised the elephant corps. ",
            "keyString": "206898s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After Alexander's death the Eastern part of his\nempire came under",
            "optionA": "  Seleucus Nicator ",
            "optionB": "  Menander ",
            "optionC": "  Rudradaman ",
            "optionD": "  Kanishka ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the death of Alexander in June 323 BC, Seleucus initially supported Perdiccas, the regent of Alexander's empire, and was appointed Commander of the Companions and chiliarch at the Partition of Babylon in 323 BC. Seleucus ruled not only Babylonia, but the entire enormous eastern part of Alexander's empire. ",
            "keyString": "207214s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following Kavya of Sanskrit, deal with court intrigues & access to power of Chandragupta Maurya?",
            "optionA": "  Mrichhakatika ",
            "optionB": "  Ritusamhara ",
            "optionC": "  Kumarasambhava ",
            "optionD": "  Mudrarakshahsa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMudrarakshasa deals with court intrigues & access to power of Chandragupta Maurya. The Mudrarakshasa is a Sanskrit-language play by Vishakhadatta that narrates the ascent of the king Chandragupta Maurya to power in India. ",
            "keyString": "207312s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mauryan administration was highly",
            "optionA": "  Decentralized ",
            "optionB": "  Bureaucratic ",
            "optionC": "  Centralized ",
            "optionD": "  Despotic ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t It can be appropriately claimed that the Mauryan administration system, though monarchical, was sufficient because it had the privilege of possessing successful administrators such as Chandragupta Maurya, Bindusara Maurya and Ashoka. ",
            "keyString": "255701s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Harshavardhana organised his religious assembly at",
            "optionA": "  Mathura ",
            "optionB": "  Prayag ",
            "optionC": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionD": "  Tamralipt ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarsha organised religious assemblies every fifth year of his reign at Prayag (Allahabad). He held six such assemblies during his reign. Whatever was left in the state treasury after five years, Harsha used to give it all in charity at that time. It is said that he used to distribute in charity even his personal belongings. ",
            "keyString": "255896s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The author of 'Arthashastra' was a contemporary of",
            "optionA": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta Vikramaditya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKautilya, also known as Chanakya, was believed to be the chief minister in the court of Chandragupta Maurya, a contemporary of Alexander and the first great emperor of India who ruled the subcontinent in the 4th Century BC.",
            "keyString": "256008s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which event brought about a profound change in Ashoka's administrative policy?",
            "optionA": "  The third Buddhist Council ",
            "optionB": "  The Kalinga War ",
            "optionC": "  His embracing of Buddhism ",
            "optionD": "  His sending missionary to Ceylon ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kalinga War (ended c.\u2009262 BCE) was fought in what is now India between the Maurya Empire under Ashoka and the state of Kalinga, an independent feudal kingdom located on the east coast, in the present-day state of Odisha and north of Andhra Pradesh . The Kalinga War included one of the largest and bloodiest battles in Indian history. Despite an unexpectedly fierce resistance from the Kalingans, the Maurya Empire claimed victory and annexed the state of Kalinga. Kalinga did not have a king as it was culturally run without any. This is the only major war Ashoka fought after his accession to the throne. The bloodshed of this war is said to have prompted Ashoka to adopt Buddhism. ",
            "keyString": "256110s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following Magadhan dynasties in chronological order-I. NandasII. Shisu nagasIII. MauryasIV. Hariyankas",
            "optionA": "  IV, II, III and I ",
            "optionB": "  II, I, IV and III ",
            "optionC": "  IV, II, I and III ",
            "optionD": "  III, I, IV and II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMagadhan dynasties in chronological order: Haryankas (544 - 412 BC) Shishunags (412 - 344 BC) Nandas (344 - 322 BC) Mauryans (323 - 184BC) ",
            "keyString": "256206s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct descending order of the Mauryan officers, at the district level, was",
            "optionA": "  Rajuka, pradeshika, yukta ",
            "optionB": "  Yukta, rajuka, pradeshika ",
            "optionC": "  Pradeshika, yukta, rajuka ",
            "optionD": "  Pradeshika, rajuka, yukta ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct descending order of the Mauryan officers, at the district level, was Pradeshika, rajuka, yukta. ",
            "keyString": "305667s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Indian ruler fought the Kalinga War?",
            "optionA": "  Samudragupta ",
            "optionB": "  Chandragupta ",
            "optionC": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionD": "  Ashoka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kalinga War (ended c. 262 BCE) was fought in what is now India between the Maurya Empire under Ashoka and the state of Kalinga, an independent feudal kingdom located on the east coast, in the present-day state of Odisha and north of Andhra Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "305873s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was ruler from The Kushan dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Vikarmaditya ",
            "optionB": "  Danti Durga ",
            "optionC": "  Khadphises I ",
            "optionD": "  Pushyamitra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVima Kadphises was a Kushan emperor from approximately 90 -100 CE. According to the Rabatak inscription, he was the son of Vima Takto and the father of Kanishka. ",
            "keyString": "306521s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ruler of Kharavela was the greatest ruler of which Chedi Dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Cholamandalam ",
            "optionB": "  Kalinga ",
            "optionC": "  Kannoj ",
            "optionD": "  Purushpura ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Kharavela was a king of Kalinga in present-day Odisha, India. He ruled somewhere around first or second century BCE. His name is also transliterated as Kharabe\u1e37a. ",
            "keyString": "307081s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Purushapura is the other name for",
            "optionA": "  Patna ",
            "optionB": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionC": "  Peshawar ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPushkalavati (now known by the name of Charsadda) was the previous capital of NWFP and the Kushan King Kanishka changed the capital from it to Purushapura (now know as Peshawar) in the 2nd century. The name Peshawar has been derived from the Sanskrit word meaning \u201cCity of Men\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "307585s1m18h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}